<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>JordanIrwin.net</title>
    <description>Thoughts, rants, tips, tricks, stories, truths, and lies.</description>    
    <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jordanirwin.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Watching Lost Mine of Phandelver</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in watching groups playing &lt;em&gt;Lost Mine of Phandelver&lt;/em&gt; from the D&amp;amp;D 5e Starter Set, here’s some video series that are pretty good:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hgNRe76o4_8&amp;amp;list=UUi-PULMg2eD_v5AO0PlW4sg&quot;&gt;D&amp;amp;D Starter Set: Lost Mine of Phandelver Pt 1&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCi-PULMg2eD_v5AO0PlW4sg&quot;&gt;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZxSw9F0NT7w&amp;amp;list=UUQj4ZJd2QxRHwVYQbMvcKdQ&quot;&gt;RollPlay: One Shots - D&amp;amp;D 5.0 - Part 1&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/itmeJP&quot;&gt;itmeJP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Oydevxx1mDU&amp;amp;list=UUbx1TZgxfIauUZyPuBzEwZg&quot;&gt;5th Edition D&amp;amp;D: The Mines of Phandelver - Part 1&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCbx1TZgxfIauUZyPuBzEwZg&quot;&gt;quill18&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/20/watching-lost-mine-of-phandelver/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/20/watching-lost-mine-of-phandelver/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Setting up this blog, Part 4</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Full Series: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/11/setting-up-this-blog-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/20/setting-up-this-blog-part-4/&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deploying and hosting the blog to GitHub Pages turned out to be a larger task than I anticipated. Not because it’s a complicated matter, but because I was initially confused and stuborn about how I wanted to handle it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;deploying&quot;&gt;Deploying&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-2/&quot;&gt;As I mentioned before&lt;/a&gt;, I’m using GitHub Pages &lt;em&gt;User Pages&lt;/em&gt; instead the &lt;em&gt;Project Pages&lt;/em&gt; since this will be a personal website instead of a product/project specific site. This means that the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch represents the internet facing website (instead of a branch named &lt;em&gt;gh_pages&lt;/em&gt;). I created a second branch called &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; that I use for writing and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering these facts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m using &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; for writing and &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; for hosting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have a custom bootstrap theme and compiling my own LESS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m compiling the website with Jekyll myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the workflow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write in &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commit &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compile LESS into CSS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compile into website via Jekyll&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Checkout &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove previous files from &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy compiled website from &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commit &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; to GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s alot of steps. Also, if something wasn’t right I would need to return to the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; branch and start again at Step 1. Bleh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve addressed this complexity in two ways: Each branch is checked out into their own folders simultaniously and I’ve written a shell script to handle the vast majority of the steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my current workflow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write in &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Commit &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Execute deploy.sh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;folder-per-branch&quot;&gt;Folder Per Branch&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remove the “hassle” of switching between &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; during deployments, I’ve chosen to keep them both checked out into their own folders. I did this by having two clones of my blog, one stays in &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; and the other stays in &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/content/posts/2014-07-20-setting-up-this-blog-part-4/branch_folders.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Branch Folders&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also solved another problem I was struggling with: Cleaning up the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch of old files. I couldn’t find a satisfying way to remove existing files from the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch without removing important things like .git, .gitignore, etc… While likely not the best solution, here’s the command I came up with for cleaning up (it’s executed from the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; branch folder, hence the pathing): &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;find ../../master -regex &quot;.*/master/[^.].*&quot; -exec rm -rf {} \;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why clean it up at all? Since &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; will never merge, I wanted be certain that &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; always reflected the current state of the Jekyll compiled website. Older, deleted files shouldn’t be left around. I simply just wipe out the files, copy in the new ones, and deploy (Git amazingly calculates neccessary deletes, adds, and edits correctly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;shell-script&quot;&gt;Shell Script&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant optimization was to wrap most steps into a shell script. Here’s the current version of that script, although I expect it will evolve over time. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jordansirwin/jordansirwin.github.io/blob/source/_build/deploy.sh&quot;&gt;You can find the latest version of the script here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;echo &quot;Compiling less&quot;
lessc ../content/self/self.less \
  &amp;gt; ../content/self/self.css

echo &quot;Building _site&quot;
jekyll build -s .. -d ../_site

echo &quot;Deleting master&quot;
find ../../master \
  -regex &quot;.*/master/[^.].*&quot; \
  -exec rm -rf {} \;

echo &quot;Copying to master&quot;
cp -r ../_site/ ../../master/

echo &quot;Adding to git:master&quot;
git --git-dir=../../master/.git \
  --work-tree=../../master/ \
  add --all

echo &quot;Committing to git:master&quot;
git --git-dir=../../master/.git \
  --work-tree=../../master/ \
  commit -am &quot;Deploying&quot;

echo &quot;Pushing to github pages:master&quot;
git --git-dir=../../master/.git \
  --work-tree=../../master/ \
  push origin master
  
echo &quot;Done!&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script labels the various steps, but it’s important to remember that I execute it via the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; branch inside the source/_build folder. Because I’m in another branch and another folder, there’s two things to note in this script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bash commands are given relative paths from source/_build to master.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Git commands are using –git-dir and –work-tree to indicate operations are for the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this script I can write and commit as needed, then run a single shell command to compile, synchronize with &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt;, and deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;previewing&quot;&gt;Previewing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I can write and deploy, I realized the need to preview all of my changes (new content or website changes). Since my deploy script did everything I needed, I simply copied it and removed the steps relevant to deployment only. Here’s my test.sh shell script in current form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;echo &quot;Compiling less&quot;
lessc ../content/self/self.less \
  &amp;gt; ../content/self/self.css

echo &quot;Building and Hosting _site&quot;
jekyll serve \
  --config ../_config.yml,../_config-dev.yml \
  -w -s .. \
  -d ../_site
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main differences from deploy.sh:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jekyll is called with the &lt;em&gt;serve&lt;/em&gt; argument instead of &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does not copy to master, commit, or push to GitHub Pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One I run this script, I can preview my blog just as it would look on GitHub Pages by visiting http://localhost:4000 in my browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next Part: Custom DNS via Hover&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/20/setting-up-this-blog-part-4/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/20/setting-up-this-blog-part-4/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thoughts on D&amp;D 5e</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just over a week ago, Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons 5th Edition (D&amp;amp;D 5e) launched. In addition to the Starter Set, Wizards has also released the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wizards.com/dnd/Article.aspx?x=dnd/basicrules&quot;&gt;Basic Rules&lt;/a&gt;- a free introductory subset of the rule system as PDF (a brilliant strategy to reduce barriers to entry). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/content/posts/2014-07-12-thoughts-on-dnd-5e/dnd_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;D&amp;amp;D Logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the Independence Day break, I ran a “one shot” game using the D&amp;amp;D 5e Basic Rules. Here’s my initial thoughts on that experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: The Basic Rules don’t currently have any monsters available, but that isn’t stopping me from playing. Since I was part of the Playtest, I have plenty of materials available that are balanced enough to use.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;character-creation&quot;&gt;Character Creation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the game, I pre-generated three characters for my players. I did this because I knew we’d be tight on time and I wanted to really explore the creation process. I created a Wood Elf Cleric, Mountain Dwarf Fighter, and a Lightfoot Halfling Rogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Character creation was a familiar process, but there were a couple of noticeable differences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;the-steps-were-different&quot;&gt;The steps were different&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose a Race&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose a Class&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roll Ability Scores&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Describe the Character&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select Equipment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you don’t have to follow these steps, I enjoyed the near &lt;em&gt;anxiety&lt;/em&gt; I experienced recognizing I’d need to choose a Race (that comes with Ability modifiers) and my Class (that depends on Ability scores) &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; I knew what my Ability scores were going to be. The min/maxer in me died a little, and I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;everything-is-positive&quot;&gt;Everything is positive&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Races, Classes, and Backgrounds all &lt;em&gt;positively&lt;/em&gt; increase the character in some way. There was not a single negative modifier to be found. Role-playing games tend to be arithmetic heavy: &lt;em&gt;Roll die, add numbers, subtract numbers, compare numbers. What happened?&lt;/em&gt; This simple change has removed one of those variables. I enjoy this approach and hope it sticks around. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;backgrounds&quot;&gt;Backgrounds&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5e respects character backgrounds by making them a required element of character creation and offering mechanical benefits for playing the game. In addition to adding flavor and story guidance to the character’s personality, they also provide bonus skills, proficiencies, and other things. This is a great step toward pushing the &lt;em&gt;role-playing&lt;/em&gt; element of D&amp;amp;D, and I approve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;traits-ideals-bonds-and-flaws&quot;&gt;Traits, Ideals, Bonds, and Flaws&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While tied to Backgrounds, these are the cream of the &lt;em&gt;role-playing&lt;/em&gt; crop. Each features a vast array of character flavor and personalities to guide the players’ decisions as well as the DM’s storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;traits&quot;&gt;Traits&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help define your characters personality: Likes, dislikes, attitude, fears, mannerisms, etc… &lt;em&gt;“Nothing can shake my optimistic attitude”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“I would rather make a new friend than a new enemy”&lt;/em&gt; are examples of Traits that your character may have. Each Background has a list of Traits to roll (or choose) from, and I expect this list will only grow as the game matures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;ideals&quot;&gt;Ideals&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Define the fuel that drives your character. &lt;em&gt;“I always try to help those in need, no matter what the personal cost”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“If I become strong, I can take what I want— what I deserve”&lt;/em&gt; are beliefs that help explain what compels your character to make their decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bonds&quot;&gt;Bonds&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tie your character to something real in the world such as a person, place, race, or item. &lt;em&gt;“I owe my life to the priest who took me in when my parents died”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“I have an ancient text that holds terrible secrets that must not fall into the wrong hands”&lt;/em&gt; are example Bonds that cement the character to something tangible- a valuable storytelling resource for both the player and DM alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;flaws&quot;&gt;Flaws&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Define weaknesses, vices, and compulsions about your character than may be exploited. These are not mechanical penalties, they are storytelling tools that drive your character (or other characters and NPCs) to behave in a way that isn’t ideal. &lt;em&gt;“If there’s a plan, I’ll forget it. If I don’t forget it, I’ll ignore it”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“I can’t keep a secret to save my life, or anyone else’s”&lt;/em&gt; are Flaws rich in flavor that will no doubt make for some interesting interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;inspiration&quot;&gt;Inspiration&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we now have rich personalities, Inspiration is a mechanical bonus rewarded by the DM (or another player who has previously earned it) for role-playing your character in such a way that exhibits an element of their personality. This is a very subjective bonus, and likely rewarded at an uncommon frequency at best- but I love that the rules provide a way to reward role-playing in a meaningful way (other than EXP): Granting Advantage (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-concern-with-inspiration&quot;&gt;A concern with Inspiration&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is binary, On or Off, A player may role-play well to earn it, then have no other mechanical “carrot” for continued role-playing. Additionally, if Inspiration is awarded too frequently it will be expected and under-valued- while if too rare it will be held tight and never expended. While I think this presents possible challenges, I don’t think there’s problem with the feature. The DM and players will need to establish the value of Inspiration themselves and work through any issues it may present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;advantage-and-disadvantage&quot;&gt;Advantage and Disadvantage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a refreshing take on modifiers, Advantage and Disadvantage continue to simplify the dice math to determine results. If you have Advantage, you roll two d20s and take the highest roll. If you have Disadvantage, you roll two d20s and take the lowest roll. This is elegant because it effectively gives a +5 bonus (or -5 penalty) to a dice roll without any math. Additionally, rolling dice is a very engaging part of role-playing games- so rolling &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; dice is a great thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-concern-with-advantagedisadvantage&quot;&gt;A concern with Advantage/Disadvantage&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the odds are stacked so high in the players’ favor (or against them) that a single extra dice doesn’t seem like enough. There will be scenarios where awarding only a single extra dice doesn’t do justice to the situation. I’ve decided to award &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; d20s as needed to stay simple, but there certainly could be balance issues with this. We’ll just deal with those as they come up. I’m choosing to prioritize fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;movement-and-actions-in-combat&quot;&gt;Movement and Actions in Combat&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During combat, characters can Move and take Actions in any combination they want, as long as they have enough Movement and/or Actions to do so. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Example:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Move 10ft, attack goblin, move 10ft, attack other goblin, move 5ft&lt;/em&gt;.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect this will make combat much more dynamic and cinematic than previous editions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;proficiency-bonus&quot;&gt;Proficiency Bonus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likely the biggest simplification in 5e, the Proficiency Bonus is a blanket modifier that applies to any ability, skill, and save that your character is Proficient in. This makes character creation and game play easier, as there aren’t various bonuses applies all over the place. The Proficiency Bonus increases with level, representing the expected power increase for the character. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feature isn’t only about simplification though. Having a small, controlled bonus that applies to all rolls makes the game easier to balance and contain. The goal is to prevent characters from becoming so powerful that they become mechanically immune to most creatures and effects. I like the idea that an experienced party of adventures can be at risk against a horde of goblins. Wizards of the Coast has referred to this as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wizards.com/DnD/Article.aspx?x=dnd/4ll/20120604%EF%BB%BF&quot;&gt;Bounded Accuracy&lt;/a&gt;, and I’m excited to see how it turns out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stay-tuned&quot;&gt;Stay Tuned&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D&amp;amp;D 5e is in its infancy. In the coming months and years, additional books filled with rules and stories will continue to expand the game and its universe of worlds. I’ll reserve true judgment until after the core books are released and I’ve had ample time to use them in game play, but for now I’m certainly excited at its prospects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more information about upcoming books and news at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wizards.com/dnd/&quot;&gt;Official Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/12/thoughts-on-dnd-5e/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/12/thoughts-on-dnd-5e/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Setting up this blog, Part 3</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Full Series: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/11/setting-up-this-blog-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/20/setting-up-this-blog-part-4/&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had my environment ready, I needed to actually create the blog. While blogs &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be a complex CMS, I didn’t want mine to be. I’m a fan of recent trends for &lt;em&gt;statically compiled websites&lt;/em&gt; and GitHub Pages natively supports &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;- it was an easy match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I initially used GitHub Pages’ automatic Jekyll compilation, but quickly switched to local compilation to take advantage of newer features (at the time of writing, GitHub runs Jekyll v1.5.1 while v2.1.1 is available). The features I wanted to use were: &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/configuration/#frontmatter-defaults&quot;&gt;Frontmatter Defaults&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/plugins/&quot;&gt;Plugins&lt;/a&gt; (although I don’t actually use any plugins yet). I disabled GitHub’s by adding an empty &lt;em&gt;.nojekyll&lt;/em&gt; file to the root of my &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; branch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get started on the blog, I created a single HTML page representing the landing page. I wanted a minimal look, drawing focus directly to the content. To help visualize, I hacked in some fake posts to have content to work with. I grabbed &lt;a href=&quot;http://getbootstrap.com&quot;&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; for grid layout and theming. Of course, creating a webpage layout and styling didn’t &lt;em&gt;just happen&lt;/em&gt;, I spent hours across days fine tuning it into something I was happy with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a structure in place, I needed to get posts to dynamically show instead of being hardcoded. Jekyll uses Liquid Templates to handle dynamic behavior. Here’s a snippet of the loop I used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{% for post in site.posts limit: 10 %}
&amp;lt;div class=&quot;post well&quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;small&amp;gt;{{ post.date | date: &quot;%B %-d, %Y&quot;}}&amp;lt;/small&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;h3&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;{{ post.url }}&quot;&amp;gt;{{ post.title }}&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/h3&amp;gt;
  {{ post.content }}
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
{% endfor %}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the above block, I now had a webpage that could dynamically load the latest 10 posts. Jekyll expects posts to be in a folder named &lt;em&gt;_posts&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/posts/&quot;&gt;named in a specific way&lt;/a&gt;. I then migrated a few posts from the old blog system using &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; for content layout (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jordansirwin/jordansirwin.github.io/tree/source/_posts&quot;&gt;see my &lt;em&gt;_posts&lt;/em&gt; folder on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I had a website and some content, but for Liquid to dynamically load posts I needed to &lt;em&gt;compile&lt;/em&gt; the website into a static page. Jekyll makes it easy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;jekyll build
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boom. This created a &lt;em&gt;_site&lt;/em&gt; folder with the compiled HTML ready to go. Wait, go where?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next Part: Deploying to GitHub Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/11/setting-up-this-blog-part-3/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/11/setting-up-this-blog-part-3/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Setting up this blog, Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Full Series: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/11/setting-up-this-blog-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/20/setting-up-this-blog-part-4/&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great deal of time was spent getting my environment configured reasonably sane. By &lt;em&gt;environment&lt;/em&gt;, I mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Directory structure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Git.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Previewing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;directory-structure&quot;&gt;Directory Structure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jordansirwin/jordansirwin.github.io&quot;&gt;My directory structure can be viewed on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; (this blog and its source is wide-open for your review). I went through a few iterations, and may still go through more, but it’s a fairly standard structure for GitHub Pages + Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;git&quot;&gt;Git&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages has great documentation available&lt;/a&gt;, but it wasn’t a silver bullet. GitHub Pages requires at least two branches: One to host the blog itself and one to store the source code for generating the blog. GitHub Pages respects a magical branch called &lt;em&gt;gh-pages&lt;/em&gt; or the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch. I chose to go with &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; for hosting and &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; for the source code. Admittedly, I didn’t get this right at first (or second, third, or tenth). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I already had some source code in the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch, I needed to change things around. I created a new branch for the source code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git branch source --orphan
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, I needed to cleanup my &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch of everything but the &lt;em&gt;.git&lt;/em&gt; folder (well, anything that doesn’t start with a period (.):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;find . -regex &quot;\./[^.].*&quot; -exec rm -rf {} \;
git commit -m &quot;insert kewl comment here&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have a clean &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; and a fully loaded &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt;. I’ll never do anything directly in the &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt; branch. Everything will be done in &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt;, then deployed (&lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; merged!) to &lt;em&gt;master&lt;/em&gt;. These two branches will never merge together again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;writing&quot;&gt;Writing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deciding what to write with was easy, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sublimetext.com&quot;&gt;Sublime&lt;/a&gt;. Cross-platform, settings configured via JSON files, great plugin support, and sports a minimal UI- I love it. I currently use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jordansirwin/dotfiles/tree/master/sublime&quot;&gt;pretty basic settings&lt;/a&gt; and only two plugins: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sublime.wbond.net&quot;&gt;Package Control&lt;/a&gt; for installing packages (plugins) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://sublime.wbond.net/packages/Markdown%20Preview&quot;&gt;Markdown Preview&lt;/a&gt; for lovely Markdown syntax highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;previewing&quot;&gt;Previewing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, Markdown Preview offers some nice Markdown enhancements- including previewing via your browser. While I do use this feature when writing notes or other Markdown based documents, this blog is previewed via Jekyll for an identical match to the final product. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To setup a local copy of the blog at &lt;em&gt;http://localhost:4000&lt;/em&gt; and automatically update modified files for real-time previewing, I use this command line from my &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; branch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;jekyll serve -w
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Safari to browse the URL and refresh as I want to preview changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next Part: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/11/setting-up-this-blog-part-3/&quot;&gt;Jekyll and building the blog’s HTML&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-2/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Setting up this blog, Part 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Full Series: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/11/setting-up-this-blog-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/20/setting-up-this-blog-part-4/&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s proper that my first post on the new blogging system is about setting up the new blogging system. So meta, much wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here were my goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid WYSIWYG.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn something new and relevant.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content must be reasonably exportable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Writing should be as exciting as the content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these goals in mind, I’ve switched away from Blogger and onto GitHub Pages. But not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; GitHub Pages, a full technology stack of goodness to learn and explore with it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sublime for writing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Markdown for markup.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jekyll for static compilation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Git for source control.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GitHub Pages for hosting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hover for domain registration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I’ve dedicated myself to doing it the &lt;em&gt;hard way&lt;/em&gt; via command line- so I’ve been forced to learn a great deal more about OSX, Terminal, and Unix Commands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interest of finishing a post, I’m going to break this into multiple parts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next Part: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-1/&quot;&gt;Setting up my environment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/09/setting-up-this-blog-part-1/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Listening</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you catch yourself thinking about your response, you are not listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://leadersinheels.com/career/10-tips-on-becoming-a-connected-listener/&quot;&gt;Source: 10 tips on becoming a connected listener&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/05/16/listening/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/05/16/listening/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Apple TV Speculation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With years of speculation on Apple’s plan for “reinventing the television”, I figure it’s time for me to increase the noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Apple TV Prediction In Bullets For Guided Reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No significant changes to the existing Apple TV (other than boosted hardware specs).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overhaul to the existing UI, primarily to accommodate my actual prediction in the next point…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new, psuedo-optional, remote that’s a striped down iPod Touch. This “iRemote” is simply a thin client for the Apple TV, offering:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Apple TV navigation mirrored on the iRemote. (This is the primary, and significant, difference from the existing Remote App)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Text inputs trigger the iOS onscreen keyboard.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Apps can generate any kind of digital input device they want (game controllers!) on the entire screen of the iRemote. Generic controls available by default, including the existing Remote App controls.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Apple TV continues to cost only $99, but without the iRemote.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;iRemote bought separately for $99.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All existing iOS devices are iRemotes via an updated Remote App.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Existing Apple TVs are backwards compatible with the iRemote via a software update.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a plan like this, Apple could potentially dominate the television market without actually entering the television market. Who cares what TV you bought or where you got it from, just add on the Apple TV for your entertainment needs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;edit: Clarified that default controls would be provided for backwards compatibility. Custom controls are optional, not required.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2013/08/21/apple-tv-speculation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2013/08/21/apple-tv-speculation/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello World, again.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here we go again…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c#&quot; data-lang=&quot;c#&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;HereWeGoAgain.ConsoleApp&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Program&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;Main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;WriteLine&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Hello World, again.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2013/06/25/hello-world-again/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2013/06/25/hello-world-again/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>