<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>JordanIrwin.net</title>
    <description>Thoughts, rants, tips, tricks, stories, truths, and lies.</description>    
    <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.jordanirwin.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Lost Mine of Phandelver</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here lies actual accounts of fictional events. Spoilers exists if you haven’t yet played this adventure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;\content\posts\2014-08-17-lost-mine-of-phandelver\lost-mines.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lost Mines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 1: &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/08/17/a-dwarf-halfling-and-human-are-sitting-in-a-bar/&quot;&gt;A Dwarf, a Halfling, and a Human are sitting in a bar&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/17/lost-mine-of-phandelver/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/17/lost-mine-of-phandelver/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Dwarf, a Halfling, and a Human are sitting in a bar</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lost Mine of Phandelver, Part 1. &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/08/17/lost-mine-of-phandelver/&quot;&gt;The full series may be found here&lt;/a&gt;. Here lies actual accounts of fictional events. Spoilers exists if you haven’t yet played this adventure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Dwarf, a Halfling, and a Human are sitting in a bar, barely aware of each others presence. A gruff and tough Dwarf swings the doors open and announces available work escorting his wagon of goods south to the mining town of Phandalin. Many in the room snark at the offer, some consider it deeply, but the noted few rise to their feet and inquire for further details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gundren Rockseeker excitingly tells the three that he needs mining equipment brought south for him and his brothers. They’ve found a mine of interest and want to delve further into it- but it will take months of work and more equipment is required. “The trek could be dangerous as bandits and goblins are known to wander the route, and it will take several days at the least.” Gundren highlights the risks of the trip, but can’t hide his smile or glowing cheeks each time he mentions the mine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a deep breath, he finally looks to his audience and bolsters his loudest laugh yet. “Erdrick Gruffbeard! I didn’t know you were in town!” Cousins by blood, Erdrick takes his offer without hesitation and Gundren shows some relief knowing his own blood will take part. Looking at the others, he asks “Who be the other here, then?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Welby Greenbottle”, states the Halfling. “I’m happy to travel to Phandalin. I have family in the area I haven’t seen in ages.” Clearly not willing to say anything more, Gundren simply nods with a smile and turns to the Human. “Gosef of Thundertree. Glory comes to those who work for it, and I’m ready to work.” With a deep satisfied laugh, Gundren escorts his hired help to the wagon of goods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wagon is full of food, mining equipment, and other common items as previously declared. Gundren mounts his pony, “I’ll pay each of you 10 gold when this wagon arrives in Phandalin. I’m headed there now so I’ll be there well in advance. When you arrive with the wagon your gold will be waiting for you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party rests for the night and gets on their way in the morning. They take The High Road south from Neverwinter and a couple of days pass without event, then east down the Triboar Trial. Suddenly, the wagon stops. Ahead on the road are two dead horses blocking the wagon from passing. Small black arrows preclude from their bodies…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is more to this story! &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/08/17/lost-mine-of-phandelver/&quot;&gt;The full series may be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/17/a-dwarf-halfling-and-human-are-sitting-in-a-bar/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/17/a-dwarf-halfling-and-human-are-sitting-in-a-bar/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Critical Hits First Impressions of the D&amp;D 5e Players Handbook</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.critical-hits.com/blog/2014/08/11/first-impressions-review-players-handbook-for-dungeons-dragons-5th-edition/&quot;&gt;solid overview of the new D&amp;amp;D 5e Players Handbook&lt;/a&gt;, including useful highlights for each class.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/11/critical-hits-dnd-players-handbook-first-impressions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/11/critical-hits-dnd-players-handbook-first-impressions/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Car Blinkers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Car blinkers help other drivers predict what you are about to do. They are not indicators of what you just did or are currently doing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/11/car-blinkers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/11/car-blinkers/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Low Status of Software Engineers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://michaelochurch.wordpress.com/about/&quot;&gt;Michael O. Church’s&lt;/a&gt; intriguing article exploring the low status of software engineers to upper management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://michaelochurch.wordpress.com/2014/07/13/how-the-other-half-works-an-adventure-in-the-low-status-of-software-engineers/&quot;&gt;How the Other Half Works: an Adventure in the Low Status of Software Engineers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few fun tidbits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;… for a point that I’ll come back to, software engineers lack the social status necessary to make others invest in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For a software engineer, “relocation” is usually some shitty $3,000 lump-sum package, because “software engineer”, to executives, means “22-year-old clueless male with few possessions, and with free storage of the parental category”. On the other hand, if you’re a manager, you might be seen as a real human being with actual concerns about relocating to another part of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;What most of us don’t realize is that this culture of mandatory “passion” lowers our social status, because it encourages us to work unreasonably hard and irrespective of conditions. The fastest way to lose social status is to show acceptance of low social status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If programmers want to be taken seriously, and we should be taken seriously and we certainly should want this, we’re going to have to take stock of our compromised position and fix it, even if that’s “getting political”. We’re going to have to stop glorifying pointless self-sacrifice for what is ultimately someone else’s business transaction, and start asserting ourselves and our values. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go read it yourself. Please. You deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/10/the-low-status-of-software-engineers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/10/the-low-status-of-software-engineers/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Value was either too large or too small for a UInt32</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Useless error message in Visual Studio when committing code into TFS that hasn’t been saved. It’s both uninformative and completely disconnected from the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I agree that commiting unsaved code into source control should be prevented, I also believe a reasonable error message to identify the problem is too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/06/value-was-either-too-large-or-too-small/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/06/value-was-either-too-large-or-too-small/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How Gary Gygax Lost Control of Dungeons &amp; Dragons</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In only ninety minutes, Gygax watched control of TSR transfer to a non-gamer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@increment/the-ambush-at-sheridan-springs-3a29d07f6836&quot;&gt;A very detailed history of Gary Gygax and the founding (and dismantle) of TSR&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/docetist&quot;&gt;Jon Peterson&lt;/a&gt;, “An author investigating the history of wargames and role-playing games.”&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/04/how-gary-gygax-lost-control-of-dungeons-and-dragons/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/08/04/how-gary-gygax-lost-control-of-dungeons-and-dragons/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>D&amp;D House Rules</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With D&amp;amp;D 5e launched and new campaigns firing up all around the globe, I thought I’d call out common house rules I like to use. These rules aren’t new or groundbreaking, and are heavily influenced from various systems I’ve played throughout my life. I simply enjoy playing games that have some flavor of these rules, so I apply them as neccessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each rule will be its own post, so here’s a Master List:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rule-skill-check-uncertainty/&quot;&gt;Skill Check Uncertainty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rule-retrying-a-skill-check/&quot;&gt;Retrying a skill check&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rule-critical-fumble/&quot;&gt;Critical Fumble&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rules/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rules/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>D&amp;D House Rule&amp;#58; Skill Check Uncertainty</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rules/&quot;&gt;D&amp;amp;D House Rules&lt;/a&gt; series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult for players to not meta-game dice rolls (ie: Low rolls are assumed failure and high rolls success). To help avoid this belief, during many Skill Checks I secretely roll a d20 as well. If my roll is a Natural 20, then the player’s result is reversed: Success = Failure, Failure = Success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; do this and it’s very subjective when I do- mainly when characters are attempting things with a natural element of uncertainly. Also, I frequently pre-roll a list of d20 results ahead of time and reference it instead of rolling real-time (expedited and even more secretive). If the player rolled a Natural 20 or Natural 1, I don’t do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;example&quot;&gt;Example&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terg wants to check for signs of an ambush ahead. He rolls a Perception check and nails it with a 19 + 7 (26). This is an outstanding number, so generally the player expects correct information. My roll, though, was a Natural 20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Confident in his awareness, Terg is certain there is no ambush ahead. The party marches forward without much caution and pays for it with a suprise attack of wargs leaping from the woods!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terg overlooked a subtle paw track on the road, a fresh and clear sign of wargs ahead. Another player could have noticed the tracks, but Terg did not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this rule isn’t to undo a characters success, it’s to remind the players that they can’t assume their characters are right or wrong based on the dice rolls alone. Had Terg rolled a 3 and me a Natural 20, he may have concluded the same thing- but noticed the track at the last second before they marched on.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rule-skill-check-uncertainty/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rule-skill-check-uncertainty/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>D&amp;D House Rule&amp;#58; Retrying a Skill Check</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rules/&quot;&gt;D&amp;amp;D House Rules&lt;/a&gt; series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a player fails a skill check and there’s no good reason they can’t just try again. Most systems allow the player to &lt;em&gt;Take 10&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Take 20&lt;/em&gt;, which is an acceptable way to handle most scenarios. Otherwise, I allow the player check again with incrementing difficulty: Each failed check will increase the difficulty of the next check by the failure amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;example&quot;&gt;Example&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seri is a stealthy rogue that’s found herself alone with a locked treasure chest. She attempts to pick the lock (DC 15), but fails with a 11 (failed by 4). Since the player is not in combat and skillfully stealthed her way into this postiion, there’s nothing stopping her from trying again. I allow another attempt, but now the DC is 19 (DC 15 + 4). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Seri recognises this kind of lock and is confident she should be able to pick it. Knowing she’s alone and unknown, she attempts to pick the lock again (DC 19).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The player rolls terribly, a 3 (failed by 16). Now, the difficulty to pick the lock is a whopping DC 35 (DC 19 + 16).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Seri’s lockpick breaks off inside the lock and snaps loudly. You overhear someone asking “What was that?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, continued failures will identify the check as impossible or introduce new circumstances to the scenario (or both!).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rule-retrying-a-skill-check/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.jordanirwin.net/2014/07/27/dnd-house-rule-retrying-a-skill-check/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>